Guide to the Outdoor Advertising Association of America Slide Library, 1891-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Topical Series, undated
  - Subseries I
    - SLP8321-SLP9040 (Box TP13)
      - Food continued
        - Meat, Fish Products, and Rice
        - Milk/Dairy Products
        - Mustard
        - Nuts
        - Peanut butter
        - Pickles
        - Potato Chips, Crackers, and Snack Foods
        - Salad Dressing
        - Potato Chips
        - Salt
        - Sour Cream
        - Sugar
    - SLP9041-SLP9660 (Box TP14)
      - Food continued
        - Sugar
        - Vegetables
        - Jell-O Products
        - Heinz Products
        - Shortening
        - Miscellaneous
      - Aluminum Foil
      - Gasoline and Automotive (primarily gasoline/oil; roughly alphabetical by brand; includes some auto parts and service)
        - Amoco - Hancock
    - SLP9661-SLP9999 (Box TP15)
      - Gasoline and Automotive continued
        - Hancock - Shell
    - SLQ0001-SLQ0300
      - Gasoline and Automotive continued
        - Shell - Signal
    - SLQ0301-SLQ1000 (Box TP16)
      - Gasoline and Automotive continued
        - Shell - Union 76 (includes Standard/Chevron)
        - Miscellaneous
      - Pain and Cold Medicine
      - Oral/Personal Hygiene
      - Eyewear
      - Hair and Skin Products
      - Dental and Medical
      - Miscellaneous Personal Products and Retail (Includes medicines, bath, health, and beauty products, pharmacies, beauty salons, and sunscreen)
    - SLQ1001-SLQ1620 (Box TP17)
      - Miscellaneous Personal Products and Retail continued
      - Restaurants (roughly alphabetical)
        - Acapulco - Der Wienerschnitzel
        - Ice Cream Shops
        - Allenhurst - Zim's
      - Apparel, Apparel Stores and other Retail (roughly alphabetical; includes some watches, cosmetics, electronics, shopping centers, and other department store consumer goods purchases)
        - Anell's - Robinson's
    - SLQ1621-SLQ2320 (Box TP18)
      - Apparel, Apparel Stores, and other Retail continued
        - Robinson's - Zayre
        - Miscellaneous
        - Footwear
        - Miscellaneous
      - Grocery Stores (roughly in alphabetical order)
        - AG Stores - Winn Dixie
      - Airlines (roughly in alphabetical order)
        - Alaska Airlines - Western Airlines
    - SLQ2321-SLQ2980 (Box TP19)
      - Airlines continued
        - Western Airlines - World Airways
      - Transportation and Travel (Includes public transportation, bicycles, mopeds, travel agencies, cruises, vacation destinations, commerce/convention destinations, resorts, miscellaneous attractions, and shopping centers)
      - Hotels
      - Moving and Storage
      - Utility Companies (often ads featuring appliances)
      - Heating and Air Conditioning
      - Electronics and Appliances
      - Photographic Equipment
      - Laundry Detergent and Dry Cleaning
      - Household Cleaners
      - Hosiery, Footwear, and Apparel
      - Florists
    - SLQ2981-SLQ3597 (Box TP20)
      - Florists continued
      - Construction and Home Improvement (Includes building materials, floor and wall coverings, decorators, furniture stores, and mattresses)
      - Insurance
      - Lawn Care
      - Metals (Includes Aluminum, Steel Buildings)
      - Data Processing and Printers
      - Paper Products (Includes napkins, tissues, wax paper, and toilet tissue)
      - Paint
      - Plumbing
      - Political Ads
      - Real Estate
      - Campers
      - Miscellaneous (Includes massage school, zippers, and trading stamps)
      - Yellow Pages
  - Subseries II
    These slides were grouped into industry standard categories. Please see category descriptions at the end of this document to facilitate your search. Often, like materials are further grouped within these categories. For ads where identity of the product was unclear, a small Product Unclear category was created at the end of this subseries. This subseries contains slide numbers with the following prefixes: SLS, SLT, SLU, SLV, SLW, SLX, SLY, SLZ, SLJ, SLK, and SLL.
    - Apparel (Box TP21)
      - SLS0001-SLS0274
    - Retail
      - SLS0275-SLS0693
    - Retail (Box TP22)
      - SLS0694-SLS1353
    - Retail (Box TP23)
      - SLS1354-SLS1413
    - Retail / Apparel
      - SLS1414-SLS1649
    - Business and Technology
      - SLT0001-SLT0280
    - Business and Technology (Box TP24)
      - SLT0281-SLT0980
    - Business and Technology (Box TP25)
      - SLT0981-SLT1640
    - Business and Technology (Box TP26)
      - SLT1641-SLT2340
    - Business and Technology (Box TP27)
      - SLT2341-SLT2754
    - Amusement and Entertainment
      - SLU0001-SLU0140
    - Amusement and Entertainment (Box TP28)
      - SLU0141-SLU0820
    - Transportation and Travel (Box TP29)
      - SLV0001-SLV0500
    - Transportation and Travel (Box TP30)
      - SLV0501-SLV1200
    - Transportation and Travel (Box TP31)
      - SLV1201-SLV1526
    - Automotive
      - SLW0001-SLW0280
    - Automotive (Box TP32)
      - SLW0281-SLW0980
    - Automotive (Box TP33)
      - SLW0981-SLW1620
    - Automotive (Box TP34)
      - SLW1621-SLW1845
    - Consumer Goods and Services
      - SLX0001-SLX0380
    - Consumer Goods and Services (Box TP35)
      - SLX0381-SLX1020
    - Consumer Goods and Services (Box TP36)
      - SLX1021-SLX1660
    - Consumer Goods and Services (Box TP37)
      - SLX1661-SLX2072
    - Beverages
      - SLY0001-SLY0080
    - Beverages (Box TP38)
      - SLY0081-SLY0560
    - Beverages (Box TP39)
      - SLY0561-SLY1020
    - Beverages (Box TP40)
      - SLY1021-SLY1427
    - Beverages (Box TP41)
      - SLY1428-SLY1947
    - Beverages (Box TP42)
      - SLY1948-SLY2467
    - Beverages (Box TP43)
      - SLY2468-SLY2967
    - Beverages (Box TP44)
      - SLY2968-SLY3332
    - Food and Restaurants
      - SLZ0001-SLZ0100
    - Food and Restaurants (Box TP45)
      - SLZ0101-SLZ0720
    - Food and Restaurants (Box TP46)
      - SLZ0721-SLZ1375
    - Public Service (Box TP47)
      - SLJ0001-SLJ0544
    - Media (Box TP48)
      - SLK0001-SLK0660
    - Media (Box TP49)
      - SLK0661-SLK1113
    - Product Unclear
      - SLL0001-SLL0117
- International Posters Series, 1925-1983, bulk mid-late 1960s, especially 1969
  Presumably, some of the ads in this series ("SLM" slides) were submitted for an International category of the OBIE awards program, a category added in more recent years. They are often in a smaller poster format to accommodate larger pedestrian audiences abroad. Some products featured include alcoholic beverages, concerts, cheese, travel, London transportation, beverages, museum exhibitions, festivals, ice cream, newspapers, and the Moscow Olympics. The slides are arranged by slide number.
  - SLM0001-SLM0621 (Box TT1)
- Construction and Creation Series, 1950s-1980s and undated
  This small series ("SLE" slides) provides perhaps the most context for the creative process. More than just the finished product, these slide images show ads at every stage of creation from idea boards to finishing touches. Most slides show images of people working on billboards, but there are also graphics showing billboard dimensions or various billboard types, photo images of workrooms, workers at worktables, workers with equipment doing actual construction, cranes hanging large billboard segments, photos of props used to put together an image, shots of billboards at various stages of completion, close shots of trim pieces, and more. The slides are arranged by slide number.
  - SLE0001-SLE0135 (Box TT2)
- Artwork Series, 1956-1973 and undated
  This series contains slide images of original artwork ("SLF" slides), usually not in any advertisement format. Artwork was sometimes submitted to OAAA as part of the OBIE Awards program. Many of these slides are labeled with the artist's name such as graphic artist and painter, Luis Gordillo. Other names found in this part of the collection include Eric Lanneau, Luis Perez Minguez, T. Mixta, Boix, A. Heras, E. Borduas, Robert Burns, F.C.B. Cadell, R. McG. Coventry, G.D. Davison, John Duncan, Crawhall, George Henry, J.W. Herald, Hornel, Leslie Hunter, W.Y. MacGregor, J.Q. Pringle, Claude Breeze, Ivan Eyre, Alex Coville, and Opura Benazon. Slides are arranged by slide number.
  - SLF0001-SLF0208 (Box TT2)
- Street Scenes and Approaches Series, 1930s-1980s and undated
  This series ("SLH" slides) contains slides with images of street scenes, often showing long approaches to billboard sites. There are examples of outdoor advertising present, but views are from a distance. These images were used in planning and preparation for construction or to show sites to prospective clients. This series reveals the most outdoor context of time and place for the advertising. While most shots in other series are close-ups of billboards, these photo images almost always show a wider scene. Slides are arranged by slide number.
  - SLH0001-0131 (Box TT2)
- Other Outdoor Advertising Related Images Series, ca. 1910-1985 and undated
  This small series ("SLN" slides) contains slides with images that did not easily fit into other categories. It includes slides of the 1975 Miss America and other campaigns designed to test or prove how well people could remember information from the outdoor medium. Various pieces of art are included, as well as a mock-up of a Signs of the Times publication cover; photographs related to a consumer survey; group portraits from industry meetings, some from as early as the 1910s; print advertisements; and portraits of advertising executives including Burr Robbins. Slides are arranged by slide number.
  - SLN0001-SLN0091 (Box TT2)
- Presentations and Presentation Slides Series, 1960s-1980s and undated
  This series contains slides organized for individual presentations, several with scripts included. The presentations at the start of the series are the most complete. As the list continues, the presentations become less complete (e.g. lacking slides, transcripts, etc.), until only loose slides from presentations are present. The intact presentations at the start of the series were created for a variety of audiences by outdoor executives often as training devices or sales tools for prospective clients. A number of the presentations were put together by the Institute of Outdoor Advertising, the marketing arm of the industry. The scripts and slides provide a mix of information not found in other series, including an introduction to the medium, comparisons to other advertising media, and history of the industry.
  Included are some historical images from the early days of outdoor advertising, but the series mostly contains mid to late 20th century images including billboard construction; shots of the creative process; labeled charts indicating the standard billboard sizes; statistics on cost, reach, frequency, and readership; and much more information about the medium in general. Though not indexed in the ROAD database, there are many images of outdoor advertising used as examples in the presentations. Some slides relate to specific companies or campaigns such as Kraft, specific markets such as Birmingham, or certain product types such as insurance or magazines. Many of the loose slides are grouped into at least partial presentations. Three of the scripted presentations have audiocassette recordings included in box PR13. There are duplicate slides in some presentations and so presumably, many were created and used in various presentations according to the need at the time. For database control purposes, individual "SLB" numbers were assigned to whole presentations.
  - Presentations: (Box PR1)
    - Outdoor Goes to College (SLB0001)
      Audio recording of script included in box PR13.
    - It Pays to be Creative (Institute of Outdoor Advertising [IOA]) (SLB0002)
      This presentation is aimed at new creative directors and discusses among other things what makes a good design and how to sell it. Audio recording of script included in box PR13.
    - Media Insurance (IOA) (SLB0003), (3 folders)
      This presentation seems designed to sell the medium to potential advertisers. Audio recording of script included in box PR13.
    - Profiles of Outdoor Advertising Readers (Outdoor Advertising Incorporated [OAI]) (SLB0004) (Box PR2)
    - Working Women (Donnelly Adv.) (SLB0005)
    - Be It Ever So Humble, There?s No Place Like Out-of-Home (IOA) (SLB0006)
    - A Presentation on Geometrics (Center for Advertising Services, 1976) (SLB0007)
    - Dialogue Presentation (IOA) (SLB0008)
    - The Giant (IOA) (SLB0009)
    - Outdoor for Retailers (SLB0010)
    - Kraft (SLB0011)
    - Common Sense (SLB0012) (Box PR3)
    - What?s New Under the Sun (SLB0013)
    - Miss America ( IOA, [1975?]) (SLB0014)
      This presentation features slides of a campaign that tested awareness. The industry used ads with Miss America's name (Shirley Cothran) and subsequent testing as proof of outdoor advertising effectiveness.
    - IOA Membership (IOA) (SLB0015)
    - Inflation (IOA) (SLB0016)
    - Target Group Index (SLB0017)
    - Best Painted Bulletin Displays - Master General Foods and duplicates (IOA) (SLB0018)
    - Cole Creative Presentation (SLB0019)
    - Garrett Orr Presentation (SLB0020)
    - Take a Look at Birmingham (SLB0021) (Box PR4)
    - Planning an Outdoor Program, Outdoor Seminar, Toronto, Ontario, 10/16/65 (SLB0022)
    - Presentation to Food Market Institute, 3/25/78 (SLB0023)
    - Outdoor for Passenger Cars (SLB0024)
    - Wall-Dog Era and Story of Outdoor Advertising (scripts only) (SLB0025)
    - Various Presentations (SLB0026 and SLB0027), (2 folders)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR5)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR6)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR7)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR8)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR9)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR10)
  - Miscellaneous presentation slides (Box PR11)
  - Glass Presentation Slides (Box PR12)
    These slides are encased in glass. Most appear to be a part of a presentation by Outdoor Advertising Incorporated including images of ads for 7-Up and Budweiser (Anheuser Busch). There is also a wide variety of street signs, spectaculars, and other signs.
  - Presentation Scripts on Audiocassette (master and use copies): (Box PR13)
    - Outdoor Goes to College
    - It Pays to be Creative, F and K (IOA)
    - Media Insurance, F and K (IOA)
Category Descriptions for Topical Series - Subseries II
Though seemingly well-defined on paper, the fluidity of these categories becomes obvious when facing thousands of diverse and often vague advertisements. If an initial search in one category does not bear fruit, try a related category. The best way to find any particular advertisement is via the ROAD database, available in early 2003. In cases where more than one product was featured in an ad, usually the most prominent item dictated category placement.
Amusement and Entertainment
This category includes ads for the following:
Bars, Casinos, Concerts, Country Clubs, Live productions (e.g. theater), Lotteries, Museums, Motion pictures, Movies, Night clubs, Race tracks, Sporting events, Teams (sports), Theaters, Theme parks, Venues (concert or event venues), Zoos.
Generally, advertisements for hotels, resorts, national parks, and whole geographic areas ("See Florida!") as tourist destinations were placed in Transportation and Travel (T and T), but there is overlap with T and T. Look in both categories for a comprehensive search. Products in the Amusement and Entertainment category are generally final destinations, as opposed to means of travel. Most television show advertisements were placed in the Media category since the network was most often a prominent part of the advertisement, but some may also be found here. Most recordings can be found in the Consumer Goods and Services category.
Apparel
This category includes ads for the following:
Clothing brands, Fashion accessories, Footwear (shoes), Jewelry
If searching for a particular apparel brand name, search this category along with "Retail," as it was often difficult to tell if a name on a billboard referred to a brand of clothing or an entire clothing store. Zippers were usually placed in the Consumer Goods category. Ads for watches may be found in Apparel or Consumer Goods and Services.
Automotive
This category includes ads for the following:
Auto parts, Auto parts stores, Auto service, Auto dealers, Auto leasing, Auto manufacturers, Motor oil, Motorcycles, Motorcycle products, RVs, Tires, Tractors
This category includes advertisements for almost anything related to cars, except gasoline. Auto parts stores are usually included here, not under Retail. Gasoline and gas stations were placed under Transportation and Travel (T and T). Ads showing both motor oil and gasoline (and/or car service) were put in the category of the item most prominent. A search for all gas stations should be completed in both this category and T and T. Often an ad advertised both car products and gasoline, or just the brand name was presented (Texaco - provides oil, gas, and car service). Sometimes it was unclear whether an ad was for an automotive or a household radiator and so both the Automotive and Consumer Goods and Services categories should be checked for those items. To search for a particular car dealer, look through subgroups of that dealer?s manufacturer within this category.
Beverages
This category includes ads for the following:
Alcoholic beverages, Non-alcoholic beverages
This category includes ads for alcoholic and non-alcoholic beverages including mixers, coffee, buttermilk, and milk. Evaporated milk is most often found in the Food and Restaurants category. For a comprehensive search of all beverages, also check the Food and Restaurants category.
Business and Technology
This category includes ads for the following:
Agricultural products, Armed forces, Banks, Builders, Business to business services, Computers, Credit cards, Financial service organizations, Freight services, Government organizations, Health care, Insurance, Manufacturing equipment, Office products, Office space, Real estate, Schools, Software, Telecommunications, Telemarketing firms, Utilities
General office supplies usually went into the Consumer Goods and Services category. Flooring and wallpaper (as well as other items used both by builders and average consumers) should be searched both in this category and in Consumer Goods and Services. Ads for lotteries can usually be found within the Amusement and Entertainment category. Car dealer financing is usually found in the Automotive category. Outdoor advertising is usually found in the Media category. Many ads featuring major appliances are without a brand name - these are probably for a utility company and were placed here. For this reason, however, some utility-sponsored ads may also be found in the Consumer Goods category. Search both this category and Consumer Goods for animal feed. Government-sponsored ads can be found in this category but if sponsorship was questionable, ads may have been put into Public Service, Consumer Goods, or some other category according to the nature of the ad. This category contains the largest variety of materials. Check other categories to complete a comprehensive search. Schools were sometimes put into the Public Services category as a non-profit and sometimes placed here.
Consumer Goods and Services
This category includes ads for the following:
Appliances, Books, Cemeteries, Dry cleaners, Electronics, Florists, Furniture, Gum, Gyms and Health clubs, Funeral services, Health and Beauty products, Hobby and craft items, Household products, Office supplies, Over-the-counter medicines, Pet food and supplies, Recordings (albums, CDs), Repair services, Sporting goods, Tobacco products, Toys and games, Undertakers, Vitamins
Household products include zippers, most flooring, and wallpaper. Office supplies were placed here but other office products are in Business and Technology. Services were also placed here including funeral homes, and dry cleaners. Cable Service ads can usually be found in the Media category. Search for watches in this and the Apparel category. Cars, motor oil, car-related products, RVs, and motorcycles can be found mostly in the Automotive category. Gasoline can be found in the Transportation and Travel category. Sometimes it was unclear whether an ad was for an automotive or a household radiator and so both the Automotive and Consumer Goods and Services categories should be checked for those items.
Food and Restaurants
This category includes ads for the following:
Candy, Confectionery, Food, Food services, Ingredients, Prepared foods, Produce
Gum, pet food, and tobacco products were most often placed in Consumer Goods and Services, although some may still be found here. Beverages, including coffee and milk, can usually be found in their own Beverages category. Grocery store and supermarket ads are usually found within the Retail category.
Media
This category includes ads for the following:
Advertising, Cable television, Direct mail, Internet services, Magazines, Newspapers, Outdoor advertising, Radio stations, Television stations, Yellow Pages
Ads for recordings (albums, CDs, etc.) and books were usually placed in the Consumer Goods and Services category.
Public Service
This category includes advertising created for a charitable cause or by a non-profit organization. Government organizations are normally listed under Business and Technology, but government sponsorship of an ad was often difficult to discern. Check this category and Business and Technology for a more comprehensive search. Political campaign and issue ads can usually be found here. Some Public Service-type ads were actually placed under the sponsor?s usual category, if the sponsor?s name was an obvious part of the ad. For instance an ad saying Don't Drink and Drive, courtesy of Fred's Funerals may have been placed under Consumer Goods and Services. Schools were sometimes put into the Public Service category as a non-profit and sometimes placed in Business and Technology.
Retail
This category includes ads for the following:
Convenience stores, Department stores, Discount stores, Drug stores, Grocery stores, Malls, Pet stores, Other Retail stores, Shopping centers, Variety stores
Some ads featuring clothing lines may have been placed here by mistake since it was often difficult to tell whether a name referred to the clothing brand or a store name. Some of these ads also feature an individual product or products carried by the retail store. If the item seemed prominent in the ad, the slide may have been indexed under Consumer Goods or Food and Restaurants. For auto parts store ads, search this category as well as the Automotive category.
Transportation and Travel
This category includes ads for the following:
Airlines, Bus lines, Cruise ships, Gasoline, Gasoline stations, Hotels, National parks, Public transportation, Resorts, Trains, Travel/Tourism services
Since gas stations but not car service are included in this category, search both this and the Automotive category for an ad featuring a company that sold gas and provided auto service. This category also overlaps a great deal with the Amusement and Entertainment category - search both categories for a comprehensive search.